Guide to the Edward M. Bassett papers, 1892-1948
Bassett, Edward M. papers, 1892-1948
- Zoning files
  - John A. Atwater, Elsie W. Atwater, Trustee - Trusts, 1932, ca.1939 (Box 12, Folder 27)
  - Estate of John A. Atwater, deceased - Correspondence, 1938-1939 (Box 12, Folder 28)
  - Estate of John A. Atwater, deceased - Judicial decisions and opinions, wills, 1938-1939 (Box 12, Folder 29)
  - Cornelia D. Plumb v. James J. Warren et al. - Correspondence re: deeds and titles, 1938-1939 (Box 12, Folder 30)
  - Cornelia D. Plumb v. James J. Warren et al. - Subpoena, titles, judicial decision, 1938-1939 (Box 12, Folder 31)
  - Wilson W. Thompson v. Louis Zackmann - Correspondence re: auto accident, 1938-1939 (Box 12, Folder 32)
  - Wilson W. Thompson v. Louis Zackmann - Judicial decision, 1938-1939 (Box 12, Folder 33)
  - Rollin G. Plumb re: purchase of No. 251 Monroe Street, Brooklyn, N.Y. - Correspondence re: house purchase, 1939 (Box 12, Folder 34)
  - Rollin G. Plumb re: purchase of No. 251 Monroe Street, Brooklyn, N.Y. - Purchase of house, legal decisions, 1939 (Box 12, Folder 35)
  - Jane W. Atwater, as executrix of the will of John A. Atwater v. J. Herbert Monds - Correspondence, 1939 (Box 12, Folder 36)
  - Jane W. Atwater, as executrix of the will of John A. Atwater v. J. Herbert Monds - Default judgements on unpaid loans, 1939 (Box 12, Folder 37)
  - Walter J. Chellew v. Emelia Langlois, et al. - Correspondence re: mortgage, leasing, 1939-1940 (Box 12, Folder 38)
  - Walter J. Chellew v. Emelia Langlois, et al. - Leasings, etc., court proceedings, 1939-1940 (Box 12, Folder 39)
  - Irving Trust Co. (re: Ada E. Carter Trust), 1939, 1941 (Box 12, Folder 40)
  - Van Nostrand, Elizabeth v. Alfred Romano - Correspondence re: negligent maintenance, 1939-1940 (Box 12, Folder 41)
  - Van Nostrand, Elizabeth v. Alfred Romano - Court case, negligence, ca., 1939 (Box 12, Folder 42)
  - Correspondence of Munley and Meade/Catherine Geary v. Elliot K. Service, 1940 (Box 12, Folder 43)
  - Catherine Geary v. Elliot K. Service, including Edward M. Bassett - Suit for negligence, 1940 (Box 12, Folder 44)
  - Walter J. Chellew V. Harriet C. Rohde - Correspondence, 1940-1941 (Box 12, Folder 45)
  - Walter J. Chellew V. Harriet C. Rohde - Sale of house, contract, indenture, 1940-1941 (Box 12, Folder 46)
  - Mabel H. Powell v. Miss Mary B. Johnson - Correspondence, 1938-1941 (Box 12, Folder 47)
  - Mabel H. Powell v. Miss Mary B. Johnson - Sale of mortgage, 1938-1941 (Box 12, Folder 48)
  - Thompson, Pearl H. v. Frank P. Briody - Correspondence re: unpaid rent, 1940 (Box 13, Folder 1)
  - Thompson, Pearl H. v. Frank P. Briody - Court summons, lease, collection of rent, 1940 (Box 13, Folder 2)
  - Plumb v. Albano - Correspondence re: mortgages, lease, 1939-1940 (Box 13, Folder 3)
  - Heller v. Plumb, Plumb v. Albano - Mortgages, leases, judicial opinions and decisions, 1939-1940 (Box 13, Folder 4)
  - Hattie Sawtelle v. Helen F. Devine - Correspondence re: payment of deed, 1940 (Box 13, Folder 5)
  - Hattie Sawtelle v. Helen F. Devine - Estate, fee, deed, 1940 (Box 13, Folder 6)
  - Albert E. Roraback v. Helen R. Keegan - Correspondence re: foreclosure, 1940-1941 (Box 13, Folder 7)
  - Albert E. Roraback v. Helen R. Keegan - Mortgage foreclosure, 1940-1941 (Box 13, Folder 8)
  - Elsie W. Atwater - Correspondence re: legal papers, 1926-1929 (Box 13, Folder 9)
  - Elsie W. Atwater - Correspondence re: legal papers, 1930-1932 (Box 13, Folder 10-11)
  - Wyckoff v. Wells Fargo Bank and Trust Co. et al. - Correspondence re: legal affairs, 1938-1940 (Box 13, Folder 12-13)
  - Wyckoff v. Wells Fargo Bank and Trust Co. et al. - Judicial decision and opinions, 1938-1940 (Box 13, Folder 14)
  - Edward Ernast Wank v. Herman W. Gartelmann - Mortgage foreclosure, summons, 1938 (Box 13, Folder 15)
  - Lenard H. Davidow - Correspondence re: legal affairs, 1937-1939 (Box 13, Folder 16)
  - Alfred C. Hafely v. James E. Howard - Correspondence re: legal affairs, 1936-1937 (Box 13, Folder 17)
  - Alfred C. Hafely v. James E. Howard - Notices, affidavit, 1936 (Box 13, Folder 18)
  - Thomas V. Cox v. George J. Blackburn - Correspondence re: legal affairs, 1936 (Box 13, Folder 19)
  - Kaufman v. Rothenberg - Correspondence re: legal affairs, 1937-1941 (Box 13, Folder 20)
  - Kaufman v. Rothenberg - Legal decisions and opinions, 1937-1941 (Box 13, Folder 21)
  - Robert G. Brodie, 1936-1939 (Box 13, Folder 22)
  - Lake Success (Village of) N.Y. - Zoning ordinance, 1937-1941 (Box 13, Folder 23)
  - Clara C. Thompson v. Simon P. McCall - Summons, legal affairs, 1937-1939 (Box 13, Folder 24)
  - Elsie W. Atwater v. Daisy B. Yost et al. - Legal affairs, 1937-1938 (Box 13, Folder 25)
  - Harold Bartholomew - Legal affairs, 1938 (Box 13, Folder 26)
  - Clifford B. Lehmann Estate, Mrs. Dorothy B. Lehmann, Executrix, 1938 (Box 13, Folder 27)
  - Swathmore, Pa. - Zoning and legal affairs, 1937-1938 (Box 13, Folder 28)
  - Estate of Cart Stauche, deceased - Legal affairs, 1934-1941 (Box 13, Folder 29)
  - Chellew v. Leone - Hahler - Legal affairs, 1934-1943 (Box 13, Folder 30)
  - Minutes of Zoning Commission, N.Y.C., 1917-1939 (Box 13, Folder 31)
  - Regional Plan Association, Inc. - Minutes, 1930-1932 (Box 13, Folder 32)
  - Russell Sage Foundation - Minutes, 1921-1931 (Box 13, Folder 33)
  - Misc. documents re: zoning, 1912-1929, 1956, 1960 (Box 13, Folder 34-36)
  - Billboards - Zoning, permits, etc., 1919-1940 (Box 13, Folder 37-38)
  - Misc. documents re; zoning, 1913-1943 (Box 14, Folder 1-3)
  - Brief, 1914-1916 (Box 14, Folder 4)
  - Edward O. Proctor, 1936-1943 (Box 14, Folder 5)
  - Walter Chellew vs. Peter N. Leone - Correpondence re: legal affairs, 1935-1943 (Box 14, Folder 6-8)
  - Henry H. Hunt - Correspondence re: legal affairs, 1941 (Box 14, Folder 9)
  - Estate of Maud S. Fanning, deceased - Correspondence re: legal affairs, 1941-1945 (Box 14, Folder 10)
  - Estate of Maud S. Fanning, deceased - Affidavit, wills, legal documents, 1941-1945 (Box 14, Folder 11)
  - Estate of Henry D. Williams, deceased - Correspondence re: legal affairs, 1940-1942 (Box 14, Folder 12)
  - Estate of Henry D. Williams, deceased - Will, bill, 1940-1942 (Box 14, Folder 13)
  - Edward E. Wank v. Adelaide C. Gartlemann et al. - Correspondence re: legal affairs, 1940-1942 (Box 14, Folder 14)
  - Edward E. Wank v. Adelaide C. Gartlemann et al. - Tax bills, 1940-2943 (Box 14, Folder 15)
  - Edward M. Bassett v. Theodore A. Bunker et al. - Correspondence, 1940-1943 (Box 14, Folder 16)
  - Edward M. Bassett v. Theodore A. Bunker et al. - Judicial opinions and decisions, 1940-1943 (Box 14, Folder 17)
  - Edward M. Bassett - Schulman House - Correspondence, 1939-1943 (Box 14, Folder 18)
  - Edward M. Bassett - Schulman House - Bills and receipt, 1940-1942 (Box 14, Folder 19)
  - Edward M. Bassett - Schulman House - Legal affairs, 1939-1943 (Box 14, Folder 20)
  - Rubin House - Edward M. Bassett v. Sarah Rubin - Correspondence, 1939-1942 (Box 14, Folder 21)
  - Rubin House - Edward M. Bassett v. Sarah Rubin - Bills and receipts, 1939-1942 (Box 14, Folder 22)
  - Rubin House - Edward M. Bassett v. Sarah Rubin - Judicial opinions and decisions, 1939-1942 (Box 14, Folder 23)
  - Daggett - Fay anti-nuptial agreement - Correspondence, 1938 (Box 14, Folder 24)
  - Daggett - Fay anti-nuptial agreement - Legal decision, 1938 (Box 14, Folder 25)
  - Lower Merion Township, Pa. - Zoning, 1935-1946 (Box 14, Folder 26-27)
  - Annie P. Bassett v. David E. Conway et al. - Legal affairs, 1938 (Box 14, Folder 28)
  - Hauser - Apren House - Legal affairs, 1938-1939 (Box 14, Folder 29)
- Scrapbooks
  Scrapbooks previously stored in Boxes 17-22 are now available on Microfilm only.
  - 1919 (Box 17)
  - 1919 (Box 18)
  - 1892-1948 (Box 19)
  - 1907-1909 (Box 20)
  - 1911-1919 (Box 21)
  - 1919-1934 (Box 22)
- Published materials
  - Books
    - Bassett, Edward M. Autobiography of Edward M. Bassett. New York: Harbor Press, 2 copies, 1939 (Box 15)
    - Bassett, Edward M. The Master Plan. New York: Russell Sage Foundation, 2 copies, 1938 (Box 15)
    - Bassett, Edward M., Williams, Frank B., Bettman, Alfred and Whitten, Robert. Model Laws for Planning Cities, Counties, and States. Cambridge: Harvard University Press, 1935 (Box 16)
    - Bassett, Edward M. Studies on Building Height Limitations in Large Cities. Chicago: The Chicage Real Estate Board,., 1923 (Box 15)
    - Bassett, Edward M. Zoning. New York: Russell Sage Foundation, 2 copies, 1940 (Box 15)
    - Ford, George B. New York Building Zone Resolution. New York: New York Title and Mortgage Co., 1917 (Box 16)
    - Perry, Clarence Arthur. Housing for the Machine Age. New York: Russell Sage Foundation, 1939 (Box 16)
    - Perry, Clarence Arthur. The Neighborhood Unit, Heydecker, Wayne D. Sunlight and Daylight for Urban Areas, Adams, Thomas Bassett, Edward M., Whitten, Robert. Problems of Planning Unbuilt Areas, in Neighborhood and Community Planning. New York: Regional Survey of New York and Its Environs, Volume VII, 1929 (Box 16)
    - Sellin, Thorsten (ed.). Zoning in the United States. Philadelphia: American Academy of Political and Social Science, Vol. 155, Part II, 1931 (Box 16)
    - Whitten, Robert. Report on a Thoroughfare Plan for Boston. Boston, City Planning Board, 1930 (Box 16)
  - Reports
    - Board of Adjustment Zoning, Report of the Board, Annual Report Board of Adjustment Zoning. City and County of Denver, Colorado, (Four volumes), 1925-1926,1926-27,1927-28,1928-29,1930-31,1932 (Box 12)
    - Board of Estimate and Appointment of the City of New York, Report of Committee of the Whole, Building Zone Plan. New York, New York, 1916 (Box 16)
    - Citizen's Zone Plan Conference, Report of Proceedings. Chicago, Illinois, 1919 (Box 16)
    - The City Committee on Plan and Survey, Report of Sub-committee on Housing, Zoning and Distribution of Population. new York, Undated (Box 16)
    - Commission on Building Districts and Restrictions, Report of the Commisssion. Building Zones. East Orange, New Jersy, 1920 (Box 15)
    - Commission on Building Districts and Restrictions. Final Report. City of New York, New York, (published and bound., 1916 (Box 16)
    - Committee on the City Plan. Establishment of Setbacks on Court Yards in the City of New York. New York, New York, 1917 (Box 16)
    - Heights of Buildings Commission, Report to the Committee on the Height, Size, and Arrangement of buildings of the Board of Estimate and Apportionment. Report. New York, New York (published and bound)., 1913 (Box 16)
    - Library, City Planning and Zoning Committee of the Chicago Real Estate Board, Final Report. Zoning in Chicago. Chicago, Illinois, 1923 (Box 15)
    - Whitten, Robert H., Report of the Committee on the City Plan. Erection of Buildings Within the Lines of Mapped Streets in the City of New York. New York, New York, 1917 (Box 16)
  - Pamphlets
    - Bassett, Edward M. The Board of Appeals in Zoning. New York: Zoning Committee of New York, 2 copies, Undated (Box 16)
    - Bassett, Edward M. Constitutional Limitations on City Planning Powers. New York: Committee on the City Plan, 2 copies, 1917 (Box 15)
    - Bassett, Edward M. Present Attitude of Courts toward Zoning. New York: National Conference on City Planning, 2 copies, 1923 (Box 16)
    - Bassett, Edward M. Zoning. New York: National Municipal League, 2 copies, 1922 (Box 16)
    - Bassett, Edward M. Zoning. New York: National Municipal League, 2 copies, 1932 (Box 15)
    - Bassett, Edward M., Williams, Frank B. Zoning Cases in the United States. New York: Regional Plan of New York and Its Environs, 1928 (Box 16)
    - Bassett, Edward M. Zoning Practice in the New York Region. New York: Regional Plan of New York and Its Environs, 2 copies, 1925 (Box 16)
    - Brittain, Joseph K., Nichols, Charles M. Proposed Amendment to the Illinois Zoning Enabling Act. Chicago, 1923 (Box 16)
    - Planning Zoning and Problems. Papers presented at the 1931 Conferences of Westchester County Planning Federation. White Plains, New York (Box 16)
    - Purdy, Lawson, Bartholomew, Harland, Bassett, Edward, Crawford, Andrew Wright, and Swan, Herbert S. Zoning. Washington, D.C., American Civic Assn., 1920 (Box 16)
  - Public documents
    - New York. Board of Estimate and Apportionment Building Zone Resolution, 6 copies, July 25, 1916 (Box 16)
    - New York. Board of Estimate and Apportionment Building Zone Resolution, 2 copies, Oct. 3, 1924 (Box 16)
    - New York. Board of Estimate and Apportionment, Amended Building Zone Resolution, 2 copies, July 31, 1929 (Box 16)
    - New York. Board of Estimate and Apportionment, Amended Building Zone Resolution, Apr. 30, 1931 (Box 16)
    - New York. Board of Estimate and Apportionment, Amended Building Zone Resolution ,2 copies, Dec. 8, 1933 (Box 16)
    - New York. Board of Estimate and Apportionment, Amended Building Zone Resolution, June 4, 1937 (Box 16)
    - New York. Recent New York Legislation for the Planning of Unbuilt Areas (prepared by Edward M. Bassett), 2 copies, 1926 (Box 16)
    - New York. Regional Plan of New York and Its Environs (prepared by Edward M. Bassett, 3 copies, one with notes), May 1924 (Box 16)
    - New York. Regional Plan of New York and Its Environs Planning the Unbuilt Areas in the New York Region (prepared by Edward M. Bassett), 3 copies, 1925 (Box 15)
    - U.S. Congress. House. Rapid Transit Act Revision 1909. Chapter 468 of the Laws 1909, Amending Chapter 4 of the Laws of 1891. Assembly No. 2310. Bound act. (Box 16)
    - U.S. Department of Commerce. A City Planning Primer, by the Advisory Committee on Zoning appointed by Secretary Hoover, 1928 (Box 16)
  - Articles and periodicals
    - Bassett, Edward M. "Constitutionality of Zoning in Light of Recent Court Decisions." National Municipal Review, XIII, no. 9, 2 copies, Sept. 1924 (Box 15)
    - Bassett, Edward M. "How New York was Saved by Zoning." The Chicago Real Estate Board Bulletin, July 1920 (Box 16)
    - Bassett, Edward M. "Zoning." Supplement to the National Municipal Review, IX no. 5, (pp. 315-341), 2 copies, May 1920 (Box 16)
    - Hubbard, Henry Vincent (ed.). City Planning. Cambridge, Mass.: City Planning Publishing Co., IX, no. 3, July 1933 (Box 16)
    - New York Evening Post. A series of six articles by experts analyzing the transportation situation in the greater city in pamphlet titled Transit Problem of New York, 2 copies, Undated (Box 16)
    - Padgett, Dora H. (ed.). Planning and Civic Comment. Pennsylvania: Mount Pleasant Press, J. Horace McFarland Co., 1940 (Box 16)
    - Williams, Frank Backus. "The Ideals of Edward M. Bassett as I knew Him." Zoning Bulletin, no. 50, Dec. 1948 (Box 16)
  - Speeches and Presentations
    - Bassett, Edward M. "How to Open Streets and Obtain Street Improvements in the City of New York." Speech presented before the Municipal Club of Brooklyn, 2 copies, Oct. 30, 1906 (Box 16)
    - Bassett, Edward M. "Municipal Housekeeping Here and Abroad." Speech presented before the Eastern New York Section of the National Electric Light Association at a meeting held in Schenectady, New York, 2 copies, Jan. 23, 1913 (Box 16)
    - Bassett, Edward M. "Zoning Round Table." Symposium of "A Court Dissects a Planning Commission.", 2 copies, Undated (Box 15)
  - Guide
    - Advisory Committee on City Planning and Zoning, Model Subdivision Regulations. Washington D.C.: National Resources Committee, 1936 (Box 16)
  - Miscellaneous
    - Bassett, Edward M. "Zoning." City Planning (collection of papers by John Nolen). National Municipal League, 1930 (Box 16)
SEPARATED MATERIAL
Copies available through Cornell Library
Fifty Years of New York Steam Service (New York: New York Steam Corporation, 1932) CU call number: TH7641 .N53 1932
Porter L. Moore, The Renaissance of City Hall( (New York: Department of Public Works, 1956), CU call number: F128.8.C48 N4
Latham C. Squire, Zoning in New York (New York: Home Title Guaranty Co., 1948), CU call number: NAC768.N52 S411
Frank Backus Williams, The Law of City Planning and Zoning (New York: The MacMillan Co., 1922), CU call number: K3534 .W72 1922; NA9030 .W72
Land Book of the Borough of Manhattan, City of New York Desk and Library Edition (New York, New York: G.W. Bromley and Co., 1930), CU call number: G1254.N52 B86 1930 ++